<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-25T11:02:51-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Holbemn</title><subtitle>Dispatches on Therapy</subtitle><entry><title>TEST</title><link href="/TEST/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TEST" /><published>2018-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/TEST</id><content type="html" xml:base="/TEST/">&lt;p&gt;TEST&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>TEST</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 1</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 1" /><published>2018-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.1/">&lt;p&gt;I have a break between clients at the moment and I’ve got my window open as far as it can go. I figured out last fall that it’s important to open the top part of my window, rather than the bottom part, so the stacks of papers who live on my desk do not go flying. I’m airing out my office, because when you work with the public in a small 10’x14’ office, you can really accumulate some different smells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of my clients at the moment smell unbearable, but I’ve had some in the past who have come close. One session, with a particularly ripe smelling young man, I caught his scent as soon as I entered the waiting room and, being quick on my toes that day, opted to save myself and my future clients by meeting with him in the basement where we have a larger multipurpose meeting room. But my efforts weren’t quite enough, and despite the room upgrade, I found myself breathing from my mouth the whole session, and wrapping up ahead of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things have been slow this summer, but they are picking up as clients settle into a routine surrounding the school year, and as overwhelmed teachers and schools make referrals for every kid they feel has ADHD. I get terribly frustrated when things are slow. I don’t get frustrated with my clients, though some clinicians do, and I really work to not look for or place too much stock in absurd, random reasons that therapists tell themselves when clients don’t show for appointments. “It’s the weather,” is the most common one thrown around by therapists on nice days and rainy days and blizzard days and every other kind of day. I tend to get frustrated when things are slow mostly because of my suffering productivity expectation, but also because it means that I no longer have a valid excuse for neglecting paperwork such as transfers, discharges, correspondence to be sent out or documented, and a thousand other pieces of minutiae which one would never think about otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m feeling positive on the whole though. I’ve been feeling more comfortable in my role recently. Mostly it comes from being reassured that what I’m doing with clients is actually therapy and is actually helping. I don’t want this to become a requisite for me feeling good about my work, but it does feel excellent to have someone say that I have helped them. I don’t mean that in a “look at me, doing such great work,” sort of way. It’s simply a reflection of the fact that as a therapist who works primarily with people who have a difficult time communicating how they feel and what they mean, and the fact that I work in a silo, with little supervision or collaborators with any real knowledge of what I do, chances for feedback can be few and far between. And perhaps my clients are paying me lip service, but I’m not going to read too much into it and just take the boost to my esteem as it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a succulent from my cousin-in-law recently, and while it’s been sprucing up my office, it’s also losing leaves on one of the shoots. I have damn near no idea how often it needs watered, so my goal is to just keep the leaves turgid and on the stem. I think I was under watering it, as it was losing leaves at a fast clip and they were looking shriveled. Now they look bloated and ready to burst. Like all areas of life I suppose moderation is key; for plants and humans it comes down to dialing it in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Smells, Confidence, &amp; Succulents</summary></entry><entry><title>Spirituality or Psychosis?</title><link href="/Spirituality_or_Psychosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality or Psychosis?" /><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/Spirituality_or_Psychosis?</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality_or_Psychosis/">&lt;p&gt;What would you do if someone came to you and said that they were depressed, or experiencing major problems functioning in their life, but it became clear that the way that they were interpreting their faith or spirituality was a key component of their struggle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one of the tougher aspects of this line of work that I’m wrestling with now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have clients and I’ve studied and discussed case-studies where clients with psychosis or delusions have warped concepts of their faith or spirituality which make it nearly impossible for others to challenge their assumptions. Religion, which in the ideal exists as a system for living and a major support, instead becomes a fortified and seemingly impenetrable castle for the ego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychosis presents itself through the lens of our own experiences. Naturally, a Christian experiencing psychosis may interpret his or her odd perceptions, hallucinations, or delusions using knowledge from the Bible. They may believe they are prophets. They may shun people who tell them otherwise. They engage in such a zealous fervor of religiosity that they become intolerable to most folks, isolating them from positive supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things clearly and objectively identify impairment of psychosocial function. Such behaviors, formed by one’s spirituality or otherwise, and their consequences fall clearly within the scope of what defines disordered behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m honestly not sure of the best way to then rectify these behaviors and perceptions when they go awry and harm clients. We talked about this predicament in classes in my graduate work, primarily in my diagnosis and multicultural classes. The best answer we seem to have come up with in terms of a strategy for approaching it in our field is the less-than-satisfying, “it depends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But lacking much official guidance, my own approach has been to follow the same path by which the problematic thinking entered the client’s schema, and challenge it from within; Trojan horse style. Build trust. Use their lingo. Summarize and draw attention to evidence of impairment. Then challenge, slowly and carefully. I am careful to pick my battles wisely, choosing problems for intervention which are largely external, and may subtly encourage reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not been easy, particularly with one of my clients, whose Biblical knowledge is more expansive than mine. But I’ve had some results, mainly in building trust with them; validating, acknowledging, and occasionally pushing back ever-so-slightly using their own lingo and arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adventure as I’ve found has been walking closely to that barely-perceptible line of too-far and not-far-enough, recovering with the client when my challenge hits an unexpected wall, and maintaining the all-important trust. I don’t have a perfect formula, but I find the work at once exhilarating and exhausting. I’m going to continue to explore it, and will post updates, (though perhaps vague and cryptic) as I find success and failure along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Religion, which in the ideal exists as a system for living and a major support, instead becomes a fortified and seemingly impenetrable castle for the ego.</summary></entry><entry><title>That Other Client</title><link href="/That_Other_Client/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="That Other Client" /><published>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/That_Other_Client</id><content type="html" xml:base="/That_Other_Client/">&lt;p&gt;There’s a scene in every movie about A.I. where the computer or android or RoboCop develops its sentience, and I’ve come to discover that in therapy, many of my clients play out a similar type of dramatic realization. But rather than discover their own consciousness, I watch them become curious about my other clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in these scenes, they’ll broach the subject directly, asking, “what other types of clients do you see?” or, “Have you ever seen someone go through this before?” Others, take a similar, yet more less nuanced approach to their curiosity. One young lady, for example, practically insisted that I tell her an anecdote about my “craziest client.” I don’t remember how exactly I wrested myself from her inquisition, but I managed to eventually break free, having left intact the privacy of my other clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her question and this genre of inquiry highlights a curious lens for viewing one’s experience in relationship to others. Just how do others experience therapy? Where are the benefits, and likewise, the pitfalls in comparing one’s suffering relative to that of others? And what of the strange concept that each therapy relationship is different, but one half of that relationship, (me) remains constant across many clients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question for me then is: What is the significance of this curiosity, and how can it be used effectively in my practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already hinted at two of the forms that I’ve that I’ve seen client-client (or client-others) recognition tend to fall into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the, for lack of a better term, a voyeuristic type, as demonstrated as the young lady I mentioned previously. These thoughts share an origin with our instinct to people-watch, and to be curious about strange behaviors and appearances. We’ve all done this. On the city bus, in airports, at Walmart, and pertinent to my work, in waiting rooms. This often plays out when I greet or bid someone farewell in my agency’s waiting room. Collective fascination manifests in people’s faces when they tilt their heads from their phones to see who I’ve been working with, and who’s next. It’s the Tony Soprano waiting-room curiosity. My clients give one another a sort of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9nuLZ929QiA&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;ocular pat-down,&lt;/a&gt; wondering the classic thought, “what the heck is wrong with that person?” But the phrase “that person,” is indicative of the lack of depth of this form of thinking about other clients. It’s focused on the other person as a disconnected entity, with little relation to one’s self other than the coincidental. It yields little insight, and little self-reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the second type find more fascinating and useful from a therapeutic perspective. Some clients ask me questions or express thoughts about what other people do in their situations, comparing wounds, and comparing healing. Often, they make it a point to relieve, or more likely temper their own suffering by acknowledging that others have it worse. I’m sure that my own statements and reflections to them occasionally prompt this type of thinking. A large part of my counseling is validation and normalization of extreme emotions and reactions to stressors in my clients’ lives. Thus, the emphasis is on thinking about how others experience similar stressors, and subsequently the relief they obtain through various coping mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most severely destabilized clients found his focus on others’ suffering to be a crucial starting point in an offensive against his own depression. One day, in the midst of therapy, when he could hardly speak without sobbing, he said, “I was walking out of here the other day and thought to myself, ‘That dude works with rape victims; there are people who have it worse than me.’” I did not tell him that I, in fact, had not yet worked with disclosed rape victims. But instead, I inquired about what he felt that his sense of empathy for others, even in the midst of deep personal suffering, meant to him. We took this moment and reflected on the importance of validation of one’s own experiences, and the separate, but equally important act of gaining perspective. His is a success story, because he used this moment to ground himself, and went on to develop more nuanced and tailored coping skills as a result. This initial sense of people going through experiences outside of one’s own broke through the fog and allowed us a jumping off point in therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to become proficient both at recognizing, and capitalizing on these initial sparks of empathy experienced by my clients during moments when empathy is hardest to come by. Recognizing the suffering of others while simultaneously feeling as if the world is bearing down upon you is an unbelievable feat of human resilience. I want to empower clients to recognize and harness that strength and bend it to their will, allowing it to be a weapon against their own suffering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Collective fascination manifests in people’s faces when they tilt their heads from their phones to see who I’ve been working with, and who’s next. It’s the Tony Soprano waiting-room curiosity.</summary></entry><entry><title>We Back</title><link href="/We_Back/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Back" /><published>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/We_Back</id><content type="html" xml:base="/We_Back/">&lt;p&gt;I’d love to know the statistic of personal blogs that have had a dead period of such length that they require a “this space is back,” post such as this one. A high percentage would of course validate me for this extended hiatus, but in lieu of such a figure, I’ll just provide excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has been a flurry of activity and growth, the likes of which were prohibitive not just of pursuit of this creative outlet, but also of seeing good friends, attending family events, catching my favorite bands in town, etc. It’s been busy. But, I’m pleased to announce, (much like a distasteful/annoying/self-congratulatory Facebook post) that this period of my life has paid off, and I find myself currently employed as a full-time, licensed outpatient therapist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel like going through the details of all that the past year has held. Nor do I have the attention span or audacity to write a post of the length that it would require to catch this space up. What I will do however, is start maintaining this space at a more regular clip, and necessarily, it will contain anecdotes and reflections on my journey over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts will also look slightly different, mainly in their form, somewhat in their content. I would like to take a leaf out of a good friend’s book and hone my writing to be more succinct, but I’m afraid that I’m a bit of a windbag on the page. Don’t fear for my clients; I’m less of one in the office (or so I’d like to think…) At any rate however, my posts will be less New Yorker wannabe-esque, and will be more true to this site’s tag line, dispatches. I find myself with snippets of ideas and thoughts throughout each week of therapy that I feel deserve documenting before they drift off into the ether of my mind. With any luck, perhaps someone else finds them worthy also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one update I feel compelled to share relevant to the reboot of this blog, it’s that the most surprising aspect of my experience so far has been my delving, and mainly being &lt;i&gt;pulled&lt;/i&gt; deeper into my faith. I could not have foreseen the importance of faith as such a cornerstone of my work with many of my clients. The vast majority of them are Christians, disengaged Christians, or folks who are interested in pursuing spirituality. I had no idea that I would be so shaped by them and their generous displays of testimony. I also find myself employed by a faith-based organization and surrounded by believers who speak so earnestly about their faith, who are so consistently guided by their faith, that I’ve found it impossible not to admire them and amplify God’s voice in my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll see where this goes, but I can’t imagine this space being wholly secular when my practice is being so guided and informed by my own developments as a Christian. So expect that there will be writings of a spiritual nature on here as well. I’m excited to see what happens next, and to continue to discover my therapy practice; the evolution is my favorite part. There is endless opportunity for improvement, and I’m surprised by my experiences every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest blessing of all is that for all of my efforts, my clients surprise and enrich me tenfold in return. To get to do this every day, for pay, truly seems to me as if I have exploited some tear in the fabric of the universe. To anyone looking for a job where you get to be a pirate for wisdom, plundering more than you sow, become a therapist. You won’t regret it. Stay tuned as I sift through my loot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>To anyone looking for a job where you get to be a pirate for wisdom, plundering more than you sow, become a therapist.</summary></entry><entry><title>From Cocoon to Caseload</title><link href="/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Cocoon to Caseload" /><published>2017-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a cool 3 months since my last post. How can I be expected to help folks form positive habits when I can’t even stick to my own!? Here’s hoping my clients aren’t looking for some sort of saint-like fellow who has it all figured out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wrapped up my third week of seeing clients and have already learned a veritable ton from my small caseload. I’ve had the pleasure of meeting a teenager with the wisdom and grace of an octogenarian (think Uncle Iroh from Avatar the Last Airbender). I’ve sat with crying folks, afraid that they won’t ever break painful cycles of relationships and harmful habits. Folks who come to counseling scared and worried leave empowered and hopeful for their futures, feeling better just having verbalized it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a magical process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned more over the past three weeks of counseling than I did from all of the collective hours I spent in classrooms and textbooks. The part that I’m most surprised by is that I feel that I take away just as much, (if not more) from the sessions than do the clients. My professors and mentors told me that therapy was a two-way street, but I didn’t fully believe them until I experienced it for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a relief to me too that I’m not expected to just pop out of my grad-school cocoon as some sort of fully-formed master therapist butterfly. The clinic in which I’m doing my ongoing training is wonderful for supporting my growth and for being accepting of my limitations. Likewise, I’m thankful that my supervisors and fellow counselors are pushing me to expand my boundaries and continue to challenge my own assertions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that I believe I need to work on currently is my need for progress. I’m too eager to jump into session with a client and search for immediate answers or solutions to their problems, and I haven’t worked enough on being comfortable with diving into their past in order to search for some of those solutions. They aren’t always sitting on the surface, waiting for us to pick them up and activate them. In time, I aim to become better about holding my breath and going with my clients below the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’ll be no great surprise to learn that my ego must be pruned back further also. My reactions to certain things, particularly clients cancelling or quitting have been far to “me-centric.” It’s hard for me not to assume that the reason for the cancellation or no-show certainly is some reflection of something that I did or didn’t do, when really, it could be any number of reasons that the client didn’t come. Perhaps most simply, it could be that the client wasn’t as ready for the therapy or change process as they initially thought they were. I need to be willing to accept that and support that client in my thoughts and prayers as they await their season of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all else, it’s been a complete blast. I don’t know that I could love the process and art of therapy any more. Even after a challenging session, I find myself smiling with gratitude that I get to do this as a career. I am profoundly thankful for the opportunity and for the lessons my clients have taught me thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try to do a better job writing on here, but I should probably, if we’re being candid, delete the “weekly” from my bio section. I’ll probably have more to write about now that I’m in the throes of counseling, so wish me luck, and look out for more posts soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;Here’s hoping my clients aren’t looking for some sort of saint-like fellow who has it all figured out.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>On Work to be Done</title><link href="/On_Work_to_be_Done/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Work to be Done" /><published>2016-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/On_Work_to_be_Done</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On_Work_to_be_Done/">&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to find adequate words to describe my feeling of anxiety this morning in the wake of Donald Trump’s apparent election. A volatile, openly misogynist, racist figure rode to victory on a wave of his own creation. He skillfully manipulated voters with the aid of a fractured news system where fact became secondary to feeling and perception. In this world, resentment of immigrants, longing for the “America of the past,” and unfiltered racism were allowed to emerge from the shadows of the cornfields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thus, here we are. We have on our (normal sized hands) a president who simply has no idea how to run a country, much less one as complex and obviously divided as America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things will get worse before they get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to healthcare for 20 million Americans may be threatened by the proposed repeal of the ACA. Immigrants and economic and political refugees may face rejection at our borders, the very ones that welcomed our ancestors. Millions more who are struggling here to support their families abroad could face deportation, ripping families apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most troubling of all is the culture that our children will be raised in. Millions of young Americans will spend their first years of consciousness under a president without honor or decency, who does not show respect for their existence, who shows no sign that he believes in them as equals under God and under the laws of this land. And on top of that, they will know that millions and millions of Americans welcomed the man and his discrimination with open arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waking up this morning, I’m struck with a new sense of urgency. A renewed call to action. We have work to do. We know what America can be. We need to break down the walls that isolate us. We need to work to restore facts and policies as the basis for choosing candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/an-american-tragedy-donald-trump?mbid=social_twitter&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; The New Yorker editor-in-chief David Remnick’s words&lt;/a&gt; resonate with me this morning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“. . . despair is no answer. To combat authoritarianism, to call out lies, to struggle honorably and fiercely in the name of American ideals—that is what is left to do. That is all there is to do.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to struggle. And we must also be better to one another. How do I be better and combat this rampant othering, as a therapist, as a husband, as an American?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m finding that the scripture comes up with another win. 1 Peter, 4:10 (NIV) says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Each of you should use whatever gift you have received to serve others, as faithful stewards of God’s grace in its various forms.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must go forward and serve one another with a new virility, passion. We need to live that grace. We need to be better to each other. The work begins now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . here we are. We have on our (normal sized hands) a president who simply has no idea how to run a country, much less one as complex and obviously divided as America. Things will get worse before they get better.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>A Therapist for Hillary</title><link href="/A_Therapist_for_Hillary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Therapist for Hillary" /><published>2016-11-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/A_Therapist_for_Hillary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A_Therapist_for_Hillary/">&lt;p&gt;When I decided to write this blog, my goal was to focus my writing on subjects tied to mental health and my experiences in therapy. Key to my success would be to avoid writing about politics, but there are only 5 days until the election, people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this a momentary relapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evaluating the two major presidential candidates from a therapist’s perspective, the choice is clear. Hillary Clinton must be our next president. Using the core ethical values of our field as a litmus test, veracity, equality, beneficence, non-maleficence, it’s entirely clear that Donald Trump is about as far as one can be from demonstrating those principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mere mention of a Trump presidency in one of my classes elicits visible shudders from professors and students alike. As therapists, it’s astounding to witness a nominee for president whose moral character runs so counter to our standards of being a decent person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure that there are some therapists who have become so jaded that they are now capable of doing the mental gymnastics necessary to support Donald Trump. But I have a hard time believing that they also approach therapy from a place of unconditional acceptance and celebration of the human condition. To espouse both the values inherent in therapy, and those of Donald Trump, even in different settings, would break a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if one were to entirely ignore the ever-growing list of transgressions of Donald Trump and evaluate him based on what he calls his “policy proposals” alone, it’s clear that he is a man with little perception of reality, particularly when it comes to health care &amp;amp; mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being the 7th grade-level thinker he is, Donald Trump issued a “paper” on healthcare. Released back in March, and just 1085 words long, no-one was surprised to discover that the document consisted entirely of his signature blend of complaints and sweeping, grandiose promises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All but an afterthought, only one paragraph toward the end focuses on mental health. It states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Finally, we need to reform our mental health programs and institutions in this country.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hooray. Someone on the Trump campaign recognized that combining the words “mental health” and “reform” works well with focus groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It continues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Families, without the ability to get the information needed to help those who are ailing, are too often not given the tools to help their loved ones.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay… So the country’s mental health crisis can be solved by just disseminating information to the families of those who suffer from mental health problems? Should be an easy fix! Clearly, this is someone with in-depth knowledge of the public mental health crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a good thing that the (quality) campaign staffer tasked with writing this mammoth document follows up with such well-thought out details on how we’ll fix it too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“There are promising reforms being developed in Congress that should receive bi-partisan support.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! Hard to argue with a guy like Trump who understands the issues on this deep of a level and who presents such a highly detailed plan, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if one were inclined to argue with a genius like Trump, and one were interested in &lt;i&gt;actual solutions&lt;/i&gt; to America’s public health crisis in mental health, one might find it worthwhile to engage with Hillary Clinton’s “Comprehensive Agenda on Mental Health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H.R.C. and her campaign put together a plan that not only names the real challenges faced by families struggling with mental health issues, but that also includes policy proposals that could be implemented immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It addresses: the need for early diagnosis of mental disorders, the growing rate of suicide in America, Mental Health and the prison system, addiction, access to care and integration of Mental Health and traditional medical care, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with just a quick scan, it’s clear that there’s no passing the buck in Hillary’s platform. No dancing around the issues or vague, meaningless, statements. She’s an experienced and perceptive leader, an American, and a human being who understands the immediacy with which our country needs to elevate issues in mental health to the forefront of our policy discussion about healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you know anyone who’s struggled with depression, anxiety, suicide, addiction, or any mental health problem, you can support them while simultaneously rejecting utter ignorance by casting your vote for Hillary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gets it, and he doesn’t. I’m with her, and so is my field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt; - - - - &lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources (See it for yourself):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.donaldjtrump.com/HCReformPaper.pdf&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Trump’s “Paper” on healthcare.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hillaryclinton.com/issues/mental-health/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Summary of Hillary’s Comprehensive Plan on Mental Health, (longer than Trump’s entire healthcare “Paper”).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/08/29/hillary-clintons-comprehensive-agenda-on-mental-health/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Hillary’s Full Brief.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><summary>&quot;In evaluating the two major presidential candidates from a therapist’s perspective, the choice is clear. Hillary Clinton must be our next president.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>On Spirit &amp;amp; Scale</title><link href="/On_Spirit_&_Scale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Spirit &amp; Scale" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/On_Spirit_&amp;_Scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On_Spirit_&amp;_Scale/">&lt;p&gt;A girl we grew up with is in her final days of life. She is 21 and for the past two or three years has been battling a wicked form of cancer that has puzzled oncologists near and far. She is one of the most pure people that anyone has ever met, always with a kind word for others, and a generosity of spirit that you come across only a few times in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a tough time for anyone who knows her. This isn’t the way things are supposed to happen. But right now, the question I ask right now isn’t “why.” As a matter of fact, and this is odd for a therapist to admit, I’m not finding questions to ask at all right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason for my lack of questions goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are powers and forces that exist beyond our ability to comprehend. I believe that God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons or miracles I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow me to walk you through my logic, or perhaps my lack thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll begin with the exposition of applicable laws and assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with an oldie, but goodie. Newton’s third law of motion (yeah, I checked to ensure I had the number right) states that for every action there is an equal and opposite reaction. For every force exerted, a force of equal magnitude is exerted right back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re off to a great start. Let’s stick with the physics track for another one. We’ll call the universe a closed system for our own purposes here and note that within closed systems, energy, like matter, can neither be destroyed nor created. Instead it is conserved and simply changes into different forms. Swell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I believe that spirit is energy that we all possess. However you want to define it, positive energy, good juju, whatever, spirit is a force, and we carry it within us. Some folks do a better job of letting it shine than others, but we all have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, energy x time = power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rid myself of questions by applying this to the impending death of our friend. Here’s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that with her death, her spirit, and energy, and all of her power will be conserved and renewed. I know this. All of the energy that would have been generated over the long life she should have had (were an entirely rational force or being placed in charge of the universe) will not simply disappear. Her soul is too large, and her compassion too great to simply vanish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her power will be converted and stored, unleashed through everyone who was lucky enough to be a witness to her strength. The repercussions of her life and the spirits that she touched will be so great and so vast that no one person will be able to grasp them. Oh, we’ll try to. We’re hardwired to try to make sense of senseless things. The usual questions of “why” will fight their way back, time and again. But I believe that the entropy, the drive to disorder that the explosion of the star within this young woman’s heart is going to create, I believe it’s part of a bigger plan. One that we cannot see, and weren’t meant to. We’ll see bits and pieces, sure. The apple hit Newton, didn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months to come, there will be more events held and money raised. There will be lives changed and people touched. But the big picture, the true meaning, it won’t present itself in full to us. It’s the plan of a God bigger than anything than we were built to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to believe in that. I’m going to zoom out as far as I can, and when my brain hurts and my heart throbs for answers, I’m going to breathe deeply and recognize that God’s beyond what we were meant to know. And that’s alright.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons or miracles I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>On My Existential Honeymoon</title><link href="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On My Existential Honeymoon" /><published>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon</id><content type="html" xml:base="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/">&lt;blockquote&gt;“Suddenly there was a silence and into the night a violin sang a desperately sad tango, an unusual tune not spoiled by frequent playing. The violin wept and a part of me wept with it, for on that same day someone had a twenty-fourth birthday. That someone lay in another part of the Auschwitz camp, possibly only a few hundred or a thousand yards away, and yet completely out of reach. That someone was my wife.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floored, I fought the suspended reality created by the roar of the airplane as I set my book down and glanced over at my own twenty-four year old wife. She woke from her doze and smiled back at me, oblivious to the radical juxtaposition that had just smacked me upside the head. There was simply no way for her to know, and no way for me to convey the gratitude I felt to God for her at that moment. I let it be, and she drifted back to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two of us were not yet 48 hours married and jetting off to honeymoon for a week at a tropical resort. I had begun to delve into Viktor Frankl’s hallmark book, Man’s Search for Meaning, the first half of which is a gripping and detailed account of the horrors that he suffered as a prisoner during the Holocaust. Imprisoned for over three years at four different concentration camps, Frankl experienced inconceivable trials at the hands of the Nazis. Starvation. Torturous slave labor. Disease. Frankl narrowly escaped death, but his liberation was met with the discovery that his mother, father, and his young wife had not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of my honeymoon, my mind became filled of the differences between Frankl’s experiences and my own. Where Frankl had no agency over his circumstances, I had full control over mine. I had access to endless food and drink where he had only the occasional scrap of bread and unclean water. He had no idea of the whereabouts or safety of his wife with no means for finding out; mine was by my side 24/7 as we relished in absolute paradise together. The list expanded endlessly and it was more than obvious that my honeymooning experiences and Frankl’s imprisonment represented polar opposite experiences on the human spectrum of pleasure and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Holocaust, Frankl returned to the nothingness that awaited him in Vienna. There, he reflected on his experiences and derived universal existential themes of human spirituality and psychology from the suffering he had both experienced and witnessed. Out of his experiences, he found the philosophical evidence for the creation of Logotherapy, basing it upon the idea that man is driven not entirely by biopsychosocial drives or desire for power, but that a quest for a meaning and purpose is man’s primary motivating force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As evidence for Logotherapy, Frankl found both extremes of human spirit and perseverance in the face of unthinkable challenges. Frankl cited story after story of prisoners losing faith in the future and succumbing almost immediately to the abhorrent psychological and physiological pressures of the concentration camps. Those who were able to maintain a sense of purpose however, often fared much better against these conditions, informing his conclusion that these forces of meaning are more powerful and intrinsic than our biological drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Frankl’s experiences in the concentration camps poked a major hole in Freud’s assertion that any group of men, experiencing severe threats to his survival would be devoid of all individual differences and that, “in their stead will appear the uniform expression of the one unstilled urge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this claim, Frankl rebuked,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Thank heaven, Sigmund Freud was spared knowing the concentration camps from the inside. His subjects lay on a couch designed in the plush style of Victorian culture, not in the filth of Auschwitz. There, the “individual differences” did not “blur” but, on the contrary, people became more different; people unmasked themselves, both the swine and the saints.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl experienced first-hand the sort of differences that remained evident in men, even as they were systematically stripped of all worldly necessities. He tells of some prisoners who were promoted to capos and placed in charge of other prisoners. Some capos abused their power and treated prisoners worse than members of the S.S. had. But even amidst this suffering and threat to survival, others seized opportunities and used them to look out for his fellow man. Frankl memorably tells of the sole prisoner he encountered who ladled out soup to each individual impartially, giving equal amounts of beans and hearty ingredients to each individual in the line, regardless of nationality or background. According to Frankl, these differences, manifesting even in the face of unbelievable biological pressures, proved that man’s soul consisted of more than animal instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing these truths, I basked in surreality and hid from the tropical sun as we spent our vacation eating and lounging. Every biological need met. In the complete absence of any psychological stressors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;How can I wrap my mind around this scale of human suffering and magnitude of Frankl’s resulting wisdom when I only suffer from an inevitable mild sunburn?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;How do I make sense of these truths of human spirituality and the search for meaning at the core of our being when the only decision I need to make is what sort of food I want for dinner?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mulled over these questions throughout the week, I saw that even in these conditions of luxury, vacationers facing the slightest of challenges still found room for complaint. Folks complained about food, heat, shower door hinges, beach conditions, service, you-name-it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl, in speaking to challenges of a far more extreme sort said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“. . . in the bitter fight for self-preservation he (man) may forget his human dignity and become no more than an animal. Here lies the chance for a man either to make use of or to forgo the opportunities of attaining the moral values that a difficult situation may afford him. And this decides whether he is worthy of his sufferings or not.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can only assume that these individuals who could not find contentedness, even in the absence of any apparent physiological and psychological stressors, surely must have been suffering from issues of existence and meaning. At the very least, these guests blew off the opportunity to practice humility and grace in the face of incredibly trivial disappointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth that I found that week within Logotherapy is that both in the presence and absence of stressors, man acts in accordance with the state of his soul. Frankl said that it is the healing of this soul that is the mission of psychiatry and I hope to continue in this tradition through the therapy I provide. Most of all, I pray that I make the most of the underlying opportunities within challenges that come to face me in my own life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . my mind became filled of the differences between Frankl’s experiences and my own. Where Frankl had no agency over his circumstances, I had full control over mine. I had access to endless food and drink where he had only the occasional scrap of bread and unclean water.&quot;</summary></entry></feed>
