<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-27T00:10:05-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Holbemn</title><subtitle>Dispatches on Therapy</subtitle><entry><title>On Spirit &amp;amp; Scale</title><link href="/On_Spirit_&_Scale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Spirit &amp; Scale" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/On_Spirit_&amp;_Scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On_Spirit_&amp;_Scale/">&lt;p&gt;A girl we grew up with is in her final days of life. She is 21 and for the past two or three years has been battling a wicked form of cancer that has puzzled oncologists near and far. She is one of the most pure people that anyone has ever met, always with a kind word for others, and a generosity of spirit that you come across only a few times in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a tough time for anyone who knew her. This isn’t the way things are supposed to happen. But right now, the question I ask right now isn’t “why.” As a matter of fact, and this is odd for a therapist to admit, I’m not finding questions to ask at all right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason for my lack of questions goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are powers and forces that exist beyond our ability to comprehend. I believe that God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow me to walk you through my logic. Or perhaps my lack thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll begin with the exposition of applicable laws and assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with an oldie, but goodie. Newton’s third law of motion (yeah, I checked to ensure I had the number right) states that for every action there is an equal and opposite reaction. For every force exerted, a force of equal magnitude is exerted right back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re off to a great start. Let’s stick with the physics track for another one. We’ll call the universe a closed system for our own purposes here and note that within closed systems, energy, like matter, can neither be destroyed nor created. Instead it is conserved and simply changes into different forms. Swell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I believe that spirit is energy that we all possess. However you want to define it, positive energy, good juju, whatever, spirit is a force, and we carry it within us. Some folks do a better job of letting it shine than others, but we all have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, energy x time = power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rid myself of questions by applying this to the impending death of our friend. Here’s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that with her death, her spirit, and energy, and all of her power will be conserved and renewed. I know this. All of the energy that would have been generated over the long life she should have had (were an entirely rational force or being placed in charge of the universe) will not simply disappear. Her soul is too large, and her compassion too great to simply vanish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her power will be converted and stored, unleashed through everyone who was lucky enough to be a witness to her strength. The repercussions of her life and the spirits that she touched will be so great and so vast that no one person will be able to grasp them. Oh, we’ll try to. We’re hardwired to try to make sense of senseless things. The usual questions of “why” will fight their way back, time and again. But I believe that the entropy, the drive to disorder that the explosion of the star within this young woman’s heart is going to create, I believe it’s part of a bigger plan. One that we cannot see, and weren’t meant to. We’ll see bits and pieces, sure. The apple hit Newton, didn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months to come, there will be more events held and money raised. There will be lives changed and people touched. But the big picture, the true meaning, it won’t present itself in full to us. It’s the plan of a God bigger than anything than we were built to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to believe in that. I’m going to zoom out as far as I can, and when my brain hurts and my heart throbs for answers, I’m going to breathe deeply and recognize that God’s beyond what we were meant to know. And that’s alright.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>On Spirit &amp;amp; Scale</title><link href="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Spirit &amp; Scale" /><published>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon</id><content type="html" xml:base="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/">&lt;p&gt;A girl we grew up with is in her final days of life. She is 21 and for the past two or three years has been battling a wicked form of cancer that has puzzled oncologists near and far. She is one of the most pure people that anyone has ever met, always with a kind word for others, and a generosity of spirit that you come across only a few times in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a tough time for anyone who knows her. This isn’t the way things are supposed to happen. But right now, the question I ask right now isn’t “why.” As a matter of fact, and this is odd for a therapist to admit, I’m not finding questions to ask at all right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason for my lack of questions goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are powers and forces that exist beyond our ability to comprehend. I believe that God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons or miracles I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow me to walk you through my logic. Or perhaps my lack thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll begin with the exposition of applicable laws and assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with an oldie, but goodie. Newton’s third law of motion (yeah, I checked to ensure I had the number right) states that for every action there is an equal and opposite reaction. For every force exerted, a force of equal magnitude is exerted right back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re off to a great start. Let’s stick with the physics track for another one. We’ll call the universe a closed system for our own purposes here and note that within closed systems, energy, like matter, can neither be destroyed nor created. Instead it is conserved and simply changes into different forms. Swell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I believe that spirit is energy that we all possess. However you want to define it, positive energy, good juju, whatever, spirit is a force, and we carry it within us. Some folks do a better job of letting it shine than others, but we all have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, energy x time = power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rid myself of questions by applying this to the impending death of our friend. Here’s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that with her death, her spirit, and energy, and all of her power will be conserved and renewed. I know this. All of the energy that would have been generated over the long life she should have had (were an entirely rational force or being placed in charge of the universe) will not simply disappear. Her soul is too large, and her compassion too great to simply vanish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I believe that her power will be converted and stored. Unleashed through everyone who was lucky enough to be a witness to her strength. The repercussions of her life and the spirits that she touched will be so great and so vast that no one person will be able to grasp them. Oh, we’ll try to. We’re hardwired to try to make sense of senseless things. The usual questions of “why” will fight their way back, time and again. But I believe that the entropy, the drive to disorder that the explosion of the star within this young woman’s heart is going to create, I believe it’s part of a bigger plan. One that we cannot see, and weren’t meant to. We’ll see bits and pieces, sure. The apple hit Newton, didn’t it?
In the months to come, there will be more events held and money raised. There will be lives changed and people touched. But the big picture, the true meaning, it won’t present itself in full to us. It’s the plan of a God bigger than anything than we were built to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to believe in that. I’m going to zoom out as far as I can, and when my brain hurts and my heart throbs for answers, I’m going to breathe deeply and know that it’s beyond what we were meant to know. God’s beyond what we were meant to know. And that’s alright.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . God is bigger, more expansive, more powerful than any of us have the capacity to conceptualize. And I believe that this has to be the case, not for the observable reasons or miracles I can point to, but instead because of the times when I can’t point to a single one.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>Who’s Holbemn?</title><link href="/Who's_Holbemn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who's Holbemn?" /><published>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Who's_Holbemn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Who's_Holbemn/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Holbemn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad you’re here. If you’re anything like me, you find that the world of mental health with its various overlapping disciplines and theories can be mysterious and frankly, highly confusing. As a graduate student in Clinical Mental Health Counseling, I often find myself asking questions like, “How is psychoanalysis different than psychotherapy,” and more confounding, human questions such as “Why do I continue to act in ways that I know are bad for me,” and, “How can I find my purpose in life?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some of these questions, there are no clear answers. But rather than turn away from the inherent muddiness of these age-old conundrums, here at Holbemn, we’re going to lean in and face them head-on. Check back here often for explorations of ideas both big and small in mental health as I progress through my training to become a therapist. I’ll be sharing weekly dispatches from therapy school on what our training is like, what it takes to be a counselor (emotionally, personally, &amp;amp; spiritually), and what the process of therapy is like as a therapist. Other times, I will share my favorite mental health resources, news articles, and on occasion, commentary/criticism of how issues in mental health are portrayed by the media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping people achieve their potential through therapy is my main passion, but I also spend my time playing video games, making and consuming music, listening to podcasts, reading, and writing. I am blessed to find myself newly married to my best friend. That this is a terrible cliché, I am well-aware, but it’s the truest way I know to describe her. Together, we’re navigating the ups and downs of becoming our own family unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also a progressive Christian, purposefully embroiled in the process of discovering what this means for me as a counselor and a human being. Above all else, I believe that my faith calls me to recognize that simply by being here in the world, every person has infinite worth, and as such, an equally immense responsibility to love and affirm one another. I hope that my actions and writings reflect this attitude of love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my responsibility that I must also offer a disclaimer that I will in no way, shape, or form provide clinical or professional opinions here at Holbemn. There are a number of reasons for this, first of which being that I am writing here under a pseudonym (for the creative license it grants me), and also that internet interactions are simply not conducive to achieving meaningful assessment or therapy. Additionally, I am not yet licensed, and want to make this absolutely clear. All of this is to say that I would ask you to please consume my writings knowing that they are the personal opinions of someone who simply cares greatly for you and your circumstances, but is in no position to dole out clinical advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do happen to find yourself in the midst of a dark time due to struggles with substance abuse, interpersonal problems, depression, anxiety, or even if you simply need someone to talk to, I highly recommend that you seek out a counselor. We all have areas of our lives that we can improve, and I’ve found that obtaining impartial third party opinions through counseling is one of the most powerful tools out there for helping us to make those positive changes. Visit my &lt;a href=&quot;/resources&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; resource page&lt;/a&gt; to browse online resources as well as databases of counselors in order to find one in your area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please stick around if you are intrigued by anything you’ve read here at Holbemn! There will be new writings here each week, concerning any number of topics in mental health. Also, be sure to add your email to the subscription box if you like what you’ve read and want new dispatches delivered to your inbox (no more than two per week, I promise!) Please reach out to me if you have any comments, constructive criticism, or something interesting to share. You can reach me at holbemn(at)holbemn.xyz. Come back soon, and until then, have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holbemn&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Come ye, come ye, weary travelers of the internet! Gather round and learn about Holbemn the therapist, the person, and what's to come here at Holbemn.xyz!</summary></entry></feed>
