<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-20T09:07:54-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Holbemn</title><subtitle>Dispatches on Therapy</subtitle><entry><title>On My Existential Honeymoon</title><link href="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On My Existential Honeymoon" /><published>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon</id><content type="html" xml:base="/b-On_My_Existential_Honeymoon/">&lt;blockquote&gt;“Suddenly there was a silence and into the night a violin sang a desperately sad tango, an unusual tune not spoiled by frequent playing. The violin wept and a part of me wept with it, for on that same day someone had a twenty-fourth birthday. That someone lay in another part of the Auschwitz camp, possibly only a few hundred or a thousand yards away, and yet completely out of reach. That someone was my wife.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floored, I fought the suspended reality created by the roar of the airplane as I set my book down and glanced over at my own twenty-four year old wife. She woke from her doze and smiled back at me, oblivious to the radical juxtaposition that had just smacked me upside the head. There was simply no way for her to know, and no way for me to convey the gratitude I felt to God for her at that moment. I let it be, and she drifted back to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two of us were not yet 48 hours married and jetting off to honeymoon for a week at a tropical resort. I had begun to delve into Viktor Frankl’s hallmark book, Man’s Search for Meaning, the first half of which is a gripping and detailed account of the horrors that he suffered as a prisoner during the Holocaust. Imprisoned for over three years at four different concentration camps, Frankl experienced inconceivable trials at the hands of the Nazis. Starvation. Torturous slave labor. Disease. Frankl narrowly escaped death, but his liberation was met with the discovery that his mother, father, and his young wife had not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of my honeymoon, my mind became filled of the differences between Frankl’s experiences and my own. Where Frankl had no agency over his circumstances, I had full control over mine. I had access to endless food and drink where he had only the occasional scrap of bread and unclean water. He had no idea of the whereabouts or safety of his wife with no means for finding out; mine was by my side 24/7 as we relished in absolute paradise together. The list expanded endlessly and it was more than obvious that my honeymooning experiences and Frankl’s imprisonment represented polar opposite experiences on the human spectrum of pleasure and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Holocaust, Frankl returned to the nothingness that awaited him in Vienna. There, he reflected on his experiences and derived universal existential themes of human spirituality and psychology from the suffering he had both experienced and witnessed. Out of his experiences, he found the philosophical evidence for the creation of Logotherapy, basing it upon the idea that man is driven not entirely by biopsychosocial drives or desire for power, but that a quest for a meaning and purpose is man’s primary motivating force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As evidence for Logotherapy, Frankl found both extremes of human spirit and perseverance in the face of unthinkable challenges. Frankl cited story after story of prisoners losing faith in the future and succumbing almost immediately to the abhorrent psychological and physiological pressures of the concentration camps. Those who were able to maintain a sense of purpose however, often fared much better against these conditions, informing his conclusion that these forces of meaning are more powerful and intrinsic than our biological drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Frankl’s experiences in the concentration camps poked a major hole in Freud’s assertion that any group of men, experiencing severe threats to his survival would be devoid of all individual differences and that, “in their stead will appear the uniform expression of the one unstilled urge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this claim, Frankl rebuked,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Thank heaven, Sigmund Freud was spared knowing the concentration camps from the inside. His subjects lay on a couch designed in the plush style of Victorian culture, not in the filth of Auschwitz. There, the “individual differences” did not “blur” but, on the contrary, people became more different; people unmasked themselves, both the swine and the saints.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl experienced first-hand the sort of differences that remained evident in men, even as they were systematically stripped of all worldly necessities. He tells of some prisoners who were promoted to capos and placed in charge of other prisoners. Some capos abused their power and treated prisoners worse than members of the S.S. had. But even amidst this suffering and threat to survival, others seized opportunities and used them to look out for his fellow man. Frankl memorably tells of the sole prisoner he encountered who ladled out soup to each individual impartially, giving equal amounts of beans and hearty ingredients to each individual in the line, regardless of nationality or background. According to Frankl, these differences, manifesting even in the face of unbelievable biological pressures, proved that man’s soul consisted of more than animal instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing these truths, I basked in surreality and hid from the tropical sun as we spent our vacation eating and lounging. Every biological need met. In the complete absence of any psychological stressors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;How can I wrap my mind around this scale of human suffering and magnitude of Frankl’s resulting wisdom when I only suffer from an inevitable mild sunburn?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;How do I make sense of these truths of human spirituality and the search for meaning at the core of our being when the only decision I need to make is what sort of food I want for dinner?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mulled over these questions throughout the week, I saw that even in these conditions of luxury, vacationers facing the slightest of challenges still found room for complaint. Folks complained about food, heat, shower door hinges, beach conditions, service, you-name-it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl, in speaking to challenges of a far more extreme sort said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“. . . in the bitter fight for self-preservation he (man) may forget his human dignity and become no more than an animal. Here lies the chance for a man either to make use of or to forgo the opportunities of attaining the moral values that a difficult situation may afford him. And this decides whether he is worthy of his sufferings or not.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can only assume that these individuals who could not find contentedness, even in the absence of any apparent physiological and psychological stressors, surely must have been suffering from issues of existence and meaning. At the very least, these guests blew off the opportunity to practice humility and grace in the face of incredibly trivial disappointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth that I found that week within Logotherapy is that both in the presence and absence of stressors, man acts in accordance with the state of his soul. Frankl said that it is the healing of this soul that is the mission of psychiatry and I hope to continue in this tradition through the therapy I provide. Most of all, I pray that I make the most of the underlying opportunities within challenges that come to face me in my own life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;. . . my mind became filled of the differences between Frankl’s experiences and my own. Where Frankl had no agency over his circumstances, I had full control over mine. I had access to endless food and drink where he had only the occasional scrap of bread and unclean water.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title>Who’s Holbemn?</title><link href="/Who's_Holbemn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who's Holbemn?" /><published>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Who's_Holbemn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Who's_Holbemn/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Holbemn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad you’re here. If you’re anything like me, you find that the world of mental health with its various overlapping disciplines and theories can be mysterious and frankly, highly confusing. As a graduate student in Clinical Mental Health Counseling, I often find myself asking questions like, “How is psychoanalysis different than psychotherapy,” and more confounding, human questions such as “Why do I continue to act in ways that I know are bad for me,” and, “How can I find my purpose in life?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some of these questions, there are no clear answers. But rather than turn away from the inherent muddiness of these age-old conundrums, here at Holbemn, we’re going to lean in and face them head-on. Check back here often for explorations of ideas both big and small in mental health as I progress through my training to become a therapist. I’ll be sharing weekly dispatches from therapy school on what our training is like, what it takes to be a counselor (emotionally, personally, &amp;amp; spiritually), and what the process of therapy is like as a therapist. Other times, I will share my favorite mental health resources, news articles, and on occasion, commentary/criticism of how issues in mental health are portrayed by the media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping people achieve their potential through therapy is my main passion, but I also spend my time playing video games, making and consuming music, listening to podcasts, reading, and writing. I am blessed to find myself newly married to my best friend. That this is a terrible cliché, I am well-aware, but it’s the truest way I know to describe her. Together, we’re navigating the ups and downs of becoming our own family unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also a progressive Christian, purposefully embroiled in the process of discovering what this means for me as a counselor and a human being. Above all else, I believe that my faith calls me to recognize that simply by being here in the world, every person has infinite worth, and as such, an equally immense responsibility to love and affirm one another. I hope that my actions and writings reflect this attitude of love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my responsibility that I must also offer a disclaimer that I will in no way, shape, or form provide clinical or professional opinions here at Holbemn. There are a number of reasons for this, first of which being that I am writing here under a pseudonym (for the creative license it grants me), and also that internet interactions are simply not conducive to achieving meaningful assessment or therapy. Additionally, I am not yet licensed, and want to make this absolutely clear. All of this is to say that I would ask you to please consume my writings knowing that they are the personal opinions of someone who simply cares greatly for you and your circumstances, but is in no position to dole out clinical advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do happen to find yourself in the midst of a dark time due to struggles with substance abuse, interpersonal problems, depression, anxiety, or even if you simply need someone to talk to, I highly recommend that you seek out a counselor. We all have areas of our lives that we can improve, and I’ve found that obtaining impartial third party opinions through counseling is one of the most powerful tools out there for helping us to make those positive changes. Visit my &lt;a href=&quot;/resources&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; resource page&lt;/a&gt; to browse online resources as well as databases of counselors in order to find one in your area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please stick around if you are intrigued by anything you’ve read here at Holbemn! There will be new writings here each week, concerning any number of topics in mental health. Also, be sure to add your email to the subscription box if you like what you’ve read and want new dispatches delivered to your inbox (no more than two per week, I promise!) Please reach out to me if you have any comments, constructive criticism, or something interesting to share. You can reach me at holbemn(at)holbemn.xyz. Come back soon, and until then, have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holbemn&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Come ye, come ye, weary travelers of the internet! Gather round and learn about Holbemn the therapist, the person, and what's to come here at Holbemn.xyz!</summary></entry></feed>
