<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-17T22:04:34-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Holbemn</title><subtitle>Dispatches on Therapy</subtitle><entry><title>Holbemn Recommends No. 1</title><link href="/Holbemn_Recommends_No.1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holbemn Recommends No. 1" /><published>2018-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/Holbemn_Recommends_No.1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Holbemn_Recommends_No.1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Happy Holidays!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this installment of Dispatches on Therapy, I’m adding a new form of post, one that may feel even looser, (they thought it couldn’t be done). Though I am a therapist, I still find myself spending a highly unmindful amount of time engaging with my phone and consuming media of all sorts. And while I’m trying to curb that, I figure I might as well turn some of my browsing into something more… intentional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, &lt;em&gt;Holbemn Recommends&lt;/em&gt;! I want to take the time here and there to share a few of my favorite things from art to music to interviews and journalism which speak into and inform my therapy practice, or fuel me more personally and artistically. I hope you (mindfully) enjoy them and find some of the same inspiration that I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s kick this off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/culture/the-new-yorker-interview/love-is-not-a-permanent-state-of-enthusiasm-an-interview-with-esther-perel&quot;&gt;The New Yorker - Love Is Not a State of Permanent Enthusiasm: An Interview with Esther Perel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read any of my writing, you know that therapy still holds a lot of mystery to me, particularly in regard to how other people practice therapy. Nearly everything we do is behind closed doors, so when I get a peek behind the curtain into someone else’s practice, there’s a huge validation for all of the frustration and unknowingness that I feel about my own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I stumbled upon This New Yorker interview with marriage therapist and podcast host, Esther Perel, I dove in immediately. Esther and this interview are wonderful and filled with wisdom. If you have time, absolutely listen to the clips from her podcast which invites the listener inside real-life couples therapy sessions. My favorite snippet from the interview: “&lt;em&gt;We have gone up the Maslow ladder of needs, and now we are bringing our need for self-actualization to the marriage. We keep wanting more. We are asking from one person what once an entire village used to provide.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EdP8S0uKP5U&quot;&gt;Mandolin Orange - Live at the WGBH Fraser Performance Studio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love Christmas music a great deal, but even I find myself in need of a carol reprieve partway through the holiday season. This intimate and wonderfully engineered performance by Mandolin Orange fits the bill perfectly. I’ve had it on repeat throughout my documentation hours, and find myself perpetually distracted in the best way by Andrew Marlin and Emily Frantz’s virtuosity. If you aren’t familiar with them already, you won’t find a better or more proper introduction to the best Americana duo around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll close my first &lt;em&gt;Holbemn Recommends&lt;/em&gt; with a poem I came across by Walt Whitman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sounds of the Winter - &lt;em&gt;Walt Whitman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Sounds of the winter too,
&lt;br /&gt;Sunshine upon the mountains—many a distant strain

&lt;br /&gt;From cheery railroad train—from nearer field, barn, house

&lt;br /&gt;The whispering air—even the mute crops, garner’d apples, corn,
&lt;br /&gt;Children’s and women’s tones—rhythm of many a farmer and of
      flail,
&lt;br /&gt;And old man’s garrulous lips among the rest, &lt;em&gt;Think not we give&lt;/em&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;out yet,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forth from these snowy hairs we keep up yet the lilt.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whitman’s poem is beautiful, of optimal length, and distant to the winter rhythms I experience personally. I hardly find myself surrounded with the sort of outdoors work and quaint sounds which form the basis for Whitman’s scene. My own soundscape is formed of clients’ diverse voices, gentle keyboard clacking, and the whisper of white-noise machines (damn them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite my more urban, modern setting, the old man’s words propel me forward still as I go about my work during this Christmas season, &lt;em&gt;“Think not we give out yet, Forth from these snowy hairs we keep up yet the lilt.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Esther Perel, Mandolin Orange, Sounds of the Winter</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 5</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 5" /><published>2018-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.5</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.5/">&lt;p&gt;It’s mid-afternoon on Thursday, and I’m missing the bloated-full feeling I had exactly one week ago around the Thanksgiving feast-table. Of course I forgot my lunch in the fridge this morning, so the hunger pangs I’m experiencing are not helping things any or giving me motivation to get through my last few sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been an interesting week, though they all are in their own way. I had my fourth client of the same name enter a crisis period, joining the aforementioned three comrades in a deteriorated dangerous mental state. I truthfully didn’t even know I had that many clients of the same name, but they’re really grouping together now. I’d love for them to meet one another. I should start a group geared toward supporting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past week, I’ve been making a concerted effort to pray more, and to be more spiritually focused before going into my work. I am working to reinstate my habit to make it a point to pray each morning that I would empty myself, get out of my way, so that the Lord can flow through me and speak through my actions and my words and how I make my clients feel. When I’m able to do this, I feel more present and I feel that I do a better job of discernment. Discernment in the sense that I feel I am better able to read the needs of my clients and, as I’ve mentioned before, move them toward a view of themselves that is closer to how God views them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been struck by several cases over the past week where my clients relay things that have been said to them by close friends or loved ones that just strike me as unbelievably hurtful. I don’t think we recognize on a regular basis the impact of the things that we humans say to one another when enraged to the point where we disconnect from our frontal lobe, (the region of the brain responsible for forethought.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m incredibly blessed to have been raised in a household almost entirely free of this sort of toxicity. Where it did exist, I was almost always the progenitor. That being said, these behaviors, often perpetrated by adults, against children or young adults is just mind-boggling. Bearing witness to it, whether in person or indirectly, has really shed some light for me on why people can end up spiritually and personally broken. The impact of hearing one’s own parent saying, “I don’t want him. Nobody wants him,” (real words spoken in my office in front of the “him” being referenced) is soul-crushing. Those words aren’t unheard, nor will they ever likely be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose the biggest takeaway for me personally, having heard firsthand of some truly awful experiences, is how much of a premium it puts on my everyday interactions with others. There are all sorts of videos and think pieces on this concept that you never know what someone else is going through, or has been through, and they couldn’t be more spot on. The impact of a warm and kind interaction with someone becomes life-giving in the context of such radically hurtful past experiences; I’ve heard so from clients who have been to some dark places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know personally that this is something I need to continue to work on. My adolescent self hasn’t fully worked itself out yet, and I could absolutely stand to improve my level of generosity and mindfulness in my interactions. To not just to be passively pleasant or tolerant (or tolerable for that matter), but to find drive to be actively generous with my words and actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These pieces always end with my own takeaways from things I learn from clients, and highlight why I find this job so fulfilling and life-giving. I really do believe that I get way more out of this than my clients. I’m constantly reminded through this field, as well as my spiritual and personal pursuits to back up my words with actions. To not do so would be an opportunity missed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Hunger, Discernment</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 4</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 4" /><published>2018-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.4</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.4/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Friday, November 16th:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Do not be afraid of work that has no end.&amp;quot; Avat de Rabbi Natan &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Harrison shared this quote when he was interviewed on The Robcast with Rob Bell recently and it&amp;#39;s become somewhat of a mantra for me, grounding me when things feel daunting or overwhelming or stuck. There&amp;#39;s a lot of those feelings packed into this job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a strange week, in that I&amp;#39;ve taken my work home with me more than I intend to. Not in the, I&amp;#39;m doing notes when I should be spending time with my wife sense, but my clients are in my head more than usual. I&amp;#39;m finding myself worrying about cases and taking note of cases in which I perceive that I am stuck and not making progress. I write about this often, and I fear that it will be boring to read about. If it&amp;#39;s boring, it&amp;#39;s boring though, and I&amp;#39;m fine with that. I would prefer to be truthful and rather dull, than to come up with some artificial thread of narrative excitement to try to keep some sort of curb appeal to this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributing to my weakened resolve to separate work from life are several clients of mine who have had crises of sorts over the past week, three of whom share the same first name. This coincidence has blown my mind. Across my relatively small caseload (compared to some agencies), I happen to have three clients whose mothers chose the same name, who all happen to be melting down and declining in their ability to cope as the November rain continues to fall. I don&amp;#39;t know if there&amp;#39;s any sort of meaning to be found there, but I can say with all certainty that it&amp;#39;s just one more name my wife and I won&amp;#39;t be considering when it comes time to have children. I mentioned this coincidence to the mother of one of my clients, the name being common enough for me to share without truly disclosing any client information, and she said that the trouble is absolutely in the name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a client recently who was venting about how frustrated she was that everyone around her kept apologizing for how sorry they felt that she was going through a health condition which was causing considerable discomfort. She said she hated being treated like a victim, and couldn&amp;#39;t understand why others were responding this way. We reflected that people are made uncomfortable when they don&amp;#39;t have control over a situation, and they respond in any way they can, often by apologizing. We apologize because we naturally want to demonstrate some sort of control over the situation. If we are not able to fix the situation itself, we offer to share emotion, to adopt and shoulder some of the pain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monday, November 19th:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checking back in with this dispatch to finish writing it and man, it must have been a relaxing weekend, because I don&amp;#39;t even connect with what I was writing this past week. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got home Friday with more work to be done and upon opening my laptop, I promptly shut it and didn&amp;#39;t return to it until this morning. It was an excellent decision. I think that time to destress and disconnect, along with the prospect of a wonderfully short week has me feeling quite a bit better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready to celebrate Thanksgiving and stock up on good vibes for the next stretch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m reminded of something my pastor shared in a sermon a while back. In reference to the creation story in Genesis, my pastor commented that it&amp;#39;s significant that on man&amp;#39;s first day on Earth, God deemed it a day of &lt;em&gt;rest and focusing&lt;/em&gt;. We are to work from our rest, rather than rest from our work. While that&amp;#39;s all well and good, it certainly adds to the poetic fantastical nature of the Genesis passage. The real world can be a little bit messier than that, but it&amp;#39;s good wisdom on the whole. Sometimes it takes putting off some work and shutting the laptop to right the cycle, but I&amp;#39;m ready to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Frazzled, A Reset, Working from Rest</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 3</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 3" /><published>2018-11-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-11-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.3</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.3/">&lt;p&gt;Boy, this counseling thing is a real ride. Feeling particularly blessed and energized at the moment. There’s something about this job where when it’s good, it’s really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s this feeling I capture maybe once or twice a month. Sometimes after a session or a day of sessions with clients that go particularly well, I feel confidence and conviction that lets me know I’m making a difference and that I know what I’m doing. It feels so counter to the 98% of the job where I feel more like I did this morning as I fumbled around my house, putting on my boots and coat in the dark, stumbling out into the rain while my wife slept (dear Lord, that woman deserves this day off.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the feeling I have right now is a total high of sorts, when things click like this. I’ve never had a runner’s high, (only lows for me when I run,) but from what I’ve read, I imagine it feels sort of like that. There’s just a sense that I get when a client is progressing, and finding what we do in session useful in their lives that gets me feeling so energized, like I’m where I’m supposed to be. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving home yesterday I was listening to an &lt;a href=&quot;http://robbell.podbean.com/e/episode-86-richard-rohr-and-the-alternative-orthodoxy/&quot;&gt;episode&lt;/a&gt; of The Robcast with Rob Bell (a joyful man who loves goofy titles) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cac.org/richard-rohr/richard-rohr-ofm/&quot;&gt;Fr. Richard Rohr&lt;/a&gt; when I was struck by a divinely revised job description of sorts. My job is to help others view themselves the way God sees them. Not inherently flawed, but inherently blessed and equipped to fulfill amazing things set aside for them. I believe that the feeling I am experiencing comes directly from having a sense that I achieved that in some way or other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, the sun is coming out for the first time in days, and I can’t think of a more perfect celebration. I’m stretching out and it’s my intention to soak up both the sun and this feeling. May it carry me through the next stretch of fumbling and stumbling, and I pray my clients receive this joy as well. &lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>When it Clicks, Celebration</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 2</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 2" /><published>2018-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.2/">&lt;p&gt;It’s not a good sign for the week that I’m getting my days mixed up. It’s Tuesday of the week before I go on a week-long vacation, and in my head it’s already Wednesday. I’m a day ahead of myself and the omens keep piling up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a half-hour before my next client, but their bus brought them here early. Normally I would be inclined to see them early, as I don’t feel like wasting anyone’s time. Today however, I’m in the middle of my lunch, and with my door slightly cracked, I can hear them out in the hallway making clicking noises and whistling at a low volume to get me to poke my head out of the door. It’s not like they’re even knocking. Even that would be preferable to being signaled at like some sort of caged chimp. I will see them at precisely their appointment time, and until then I will be savoring my salad, writing, and not reinforcing inappropriate behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sorts of incidents with clients are fortunately few and far between. I have a good rapport with my clients, and even in the midst of scheduling mishaps or other frustrations, I tend to find it easy to collaborate with my clients and maintain a good relationship. The agency I work for isn’t heavily tied to other resources for clients and rarely is my word the deciding factor preventing someone’s return to work or reception of disability or whatnot. This sort of role allows the therapy to be more pure, more focused on the individual and the emotions behind their distress. I prefer very much to keep it this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in mental health, I’m bound to come across some situations with folks who are in the habit of being pushy or demanding of their providers. It’s the same in any service industry really. I usually do a good job of dealing with it, but during times of low blood sugar, my batting average suffers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m terribly excited for a week away from work. It will be wonderful to get some time to clear my head, read a good book, hopefully get refocused. As I’m getting my start in the field, I’m finding that there’s a natural rhythm to how my motivation fluctuates. Motivation might not be the right word entirely. I find myself engaged and present almost all the time for my clients, but my belief in the service I’m providing wavers, and I’m sure this affects the product I deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest thing I can relate this hot and cold phenomenon to is the natural ebb and flow of one’s spirituality. C.S. Lewis dubs this, &lt;em&gt;“the law of undulation”&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;u&gt;The Screwtape Letters&lt;/u&gt;. If my memory serves me correctly, the lesser demon Screwtape writes to his young charge that the best thing they can do to drive a wedge between their patient and “The Enemy (God,)” is to make him feel that this rhythm is a fatal flaw instead of something to be expected. I firmly believe that with my counseling, a fluctuation in intensity of my engagement and belief in it is to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week away from the game will be the best thing for myself and my clients to keep us all moving in the right direction. It’s a two-way street, after all, and I need to be recharged so I can continue learning as well. Hopefully when I come back, there’ll still be folks whistling and clicking outside my door, ready to talk and learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I hope they’ll just knock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Lunch Break, and C.S. Lewis on Undulation</summary></entry><entry><title>Dispatch No. 1</title><link href="/Dispatch_No.1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatch No. 1" /><published>2018-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Dispatch_No.1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dispatch_No.1/">&lt;p&gt;I have a break between clients at the moment and I’ve got my window open as far as it can go. I figured out last fall that it’s important to open the top part of my window, rather than the bottom part, so the stacks of papers who live on my desk do not go flying. I’m airing out my office, because when you work with the public in a small 10’x14’ office, you can really accumulate some different smells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of my clients at the moment smell unbearable, but I’ve had some in the past who have come close. One session, with a particularly ripe smelling young man, I caught his scent as soon as I entered the waiting room and, being quick on my toes that day, opted to save myself and my future clients by meeting with him in the basement where we have a larger multipurpose meeting room. But my efforts weren’t quite enough, and despite the room upgrade, I found myself breathing from my mouth the whole session, and wrapping up ahead of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things have been slow this summer, but they are picking up as clients settle into a routine surrounding the school year, and as overwhelmed teachers and schools make referrals for every kid they feel has ADHD. I get terribly frustrated when things are slow. I don’t get frustrated with my clients, though some clinicians do, and I really work to not look for or place too much stock in absurd, random reasons that therapists tell themselves when clients don’t show for appointments. “It’s the weather,” is the most common one thrown around by therapists on nice days and rainy days and blizzard days and every other kind of day. I tend to get frustrated when things are slow mostly because of my suffering productivity expectation, but also because it means that I no longer have a valid excuse for neglecting paperwork such as transfers, discharges, correspondence to be sent out or documented, and a thousand other pieces of minutiae which one would never think about otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m feeling positive on the whole though. I’ve been feeling more comfortable in my role recently. Mostly it comes from being reassured that what I’m doing with clients is actually therapy and is actually helping. I don’t want this to become a requisite for me feeling good about my work, but it does feel excellent to have someone say that I have helped them. I don’t mean that in a “look at me, doing such great work,” sort of way. It’s simply a reflection of the fact that as a therapist who works primarily with people who have a difficult time communicating how they feel and what they mean, and the fact that I work in a silo, with little supervision or collaborators with any real knowledge of what I do, chances for feedback can be few and far between. And perhaps my clients are paying me lip service, but I’m not going to read too much into it and just take the boost to my esteem as it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a succulent from my cousin-in-law recently, and while it’s been sprucing up my office, it’s also losing leaves on one of the shoots. I have damn near no idea how often it needs watered, so my goal is to just keep the leaves turgid and on the stem. I think I was under watering it, as it was losing leaves at a fast clip and they were looking shriveled. Now they look bloated and ready to burst. Like all areas of life I suppose moderation is key; for plants and humans it comes down to dialing it in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Smells, Confidence, and Succulents</summary></entry><entry><title>Spirituality or Psychosis?</title><link href="/Spirituality_or_Psychosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality or Psychosis?" /><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/Spirituality_or_Psychosis?</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality_or_Psychosis/">&lt;p&gt;What would you do if someone came to you and said that they were depressed, or experiencing major problems functioning in their life, but it became clear that the way that they were interpreting their faith or spirituality was a key component of their struggle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one of the tougher aspects of this line of work that I’m wrestling with now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have clients and I’ve studied and discussed case-studies where clients with psychosis or delusions have warped concepts of their faith or spirituality which make it nearly impossible for others to challenge their assumptions. Religion, which in the ideal exists as a system for living and a major support, instead becomes a fortified and seemingly impenetrable castle for the ego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychosis presents itself through the lens of our own experiences. Naturally, a Christian experiencing psychosis may interpret his or her odd perceptions, hallucinations, or delusions using knowledge from the Bible. They may believe they are prophets. They may shun people who tell them otherwise. They engage in such a zealous fervor of religiosity that they become intolerable to most folks, isolating them from positive supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things clearly and objectively identify impairment of psychosocial function. Such behaviors, formed by one’s spirituality or otherwise, and their consequences fall clearly within the scope of what defines disordered behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m honestly not sure of the best way to then rectify these behaviors and perceptions when they go awry and harm clients. We talked about this predicament in classes in my graduate work, primarily in my diagnosis and multicultural classes. The best answer we seem to have come up with in terms of a strategy for approaching it in our field is the less-than-satisfying, “it depends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But lacking much official guidance, my own approach has been to follow the same path by which the problematic thinking entered the client’s schema, and challenge it from within; Trojan horse style. Build trust. Use their lingo. Summarize and draw attention to evidence of impairment. Then challenge, slowly and carefully. I am careful to pick my battles wisely, choosing problems for intervention which are largely external, and may subtly encourage reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not been easy, particularly with one of my clients, whose Biblical knowledge is more expansive than mine. But I’ve had some results, mainly in building trust with them; validating, acknowledging, and occasionally pushing back ever-so-slightly using their own lingo and arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adventure as I’ve found has been walking closely to that barely-perceptible line of too-far and not-far-enough, recovering with the client when my challenge hits an unexpected wall, and maintaining the all-important trust. I don’t have a perfect formula, but I find the work at once exhilarating and exhausting. I’m going to continue to explore it, and will post updates, (though perhaps vague and cryptic) as I find success and failure along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Religion, which in the ideal exists as a system for living and a major support, instead becomes a fortified and seemingly impenetrable castle for the ego.</summary></entry><entry><title>That Other Client</title><link href="/That_Other_Client/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="That Other Client" /><published>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/That_Other_Client</id><content type="html" xml:base="/That_Other_Client/">&lt;p&gt;There’s a scene in every movie about A.I. where the computer or android or RoboCop develops its sentience, and I’ve come to discover that in therapy, many of my clients play out a similar type of dramatic realization. But rather than discover their own consciousness, I watch them become curious about my other clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in these scenes, they’ll broach the subject directly, asking, “what other types of clients do you see?” or, “Have you ever seen someone go through this before?” Others, take a similar, yet more less nuanced approach to their curiosity. One young lady, for example, practically insisted that I tell her an anecdote about my “craziest client.” I don’t remember how exactly I wrested myself from her inquisition, but I managed to eventually break free, having left intact the privacy of my other clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her question and this genre of inquiry highlights a curious lens for viewing one’s experience in relationship to others. Just how do others experience therapy? Where are the benefits, and likewise, the pitfalls in comparing one’s suffering relative to that of others? And what of the strange concept that each therapy relationship is different, but one half of that relationship, (me) remains constant across many clients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question for me then is: What is the significance of this curiosity, and how can it be used effectively in my practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already hinted at two of the forms that I’ve that I’ve seen client-client (or client-others) recognition tend to fall into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the, for lack of a better term, a voyeuristic type, as demonstrated as the young lady I mentioned previously. These thoughts share an origin with our instinct to people-watch, and to be curious about strange behaviors and appearances. We’ve all done this. On the city bus, in airports, at Walmart, and pertinent to my work, in waiting rooms. This often plays out when I greet or bid someone farewell in my agency’s waiting room. Collective fascination manifests in people’s faces when they tilt their heads from their phones to see who I’ve been working with, and who’s next. It’s the Tony Soprano waiting-room curiosity. My clients give one another a sort of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9nuLZ929QiA&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;ocular pat-down,&lt;/a&gt; wondering the classic thought, “what the heck is wrong with that person?” But the phrase “that person,” is indicative of the lack of depth of this form of thinking about other clients. It’s focused on the other person as a disconnected entity, with little relation to one’s self other than the coincidental. It yields little insight, and little self-reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the second type find more fascinating and useful from a therapeutic perspective. Some clients ask me questions or express thoughts about what other people do in their situations, comparing wounds, and comparing healing. Often, they make it a point to relieve, or more likely temper their own suffering by acknowledging that others have it worse. I’m sure that my own statements and reflections to them occasionally prompt this type of thinking. A large part of my counseling is validation and normalization of extreme emotions and reactions to stressors in my clients’ lives. Thus, the emphasis is on thinking about how others experience similar stressors, and subsequently the relief they obtain through various coping mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most severely destabilized clients found his focus on others’ suffering to be a crucial starting point in an offensive against his own depression. One day, in the midst of therapy, when he could hardly speak without sobbing, he said, “I was walking out of here the other day and thought to myself, ‘That dude works with rape victims; there are people who have it worse than me.’” I did not tell him that I, in fact, had not yet worked with disclosed rape victims. But instead, I inquired about what he felt that his sense of empathy for others, even in the midst of deep personal suffering, meant to him. We took this moment and reflected on the importance of validation of one’s own experiences, and the separate, but equally important act of gaining perspective. His is a success story, because he used this moment to ground himself, and went on to develop more nuanced and tailored coping skills as a result. This initial sense of people going through experiences outside of one’s own broke through the fog and allowed us a jumping off point in therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to become proficient both at recognizing, and capitalizing on these initial sparks of empathy experienced by my clients during moments when empathy is hardest to come by. Recognizing the suffering of others while simultaneously feeling as if the world is bearing down upon you is an unbelievable feat of human resilience. I want to empower clients to recognize and harness that strength and bend it to their will, allowing it to be a weapon against their own suffering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Collective fascination manifests in people’s faces when they tilt their heads from their phones to see who I’ve been working with, and who’s next. It’s the Tony Soprano waiting-room curiosity.</summary></entry><entry><title>We Back</title><link href="/We_Back/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Back" /><published>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/We_Back</id><content type="html" xml:base="/We_Back/">&lt;p&gt;I’d love to know the statistic of personal blogs that have had a dead period of such length that they require a “this space is back,” post such as this one. A high percentage would of course validate me for this extended hiatus, but in lieu of such a figure, I’ll just provide excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has been a flurry of activity and growth, the likes of which were prohibitive not just of pursuit of this creative outlet, but also of seeing good friends, attending family events, catching my favorite bands in town, etc. It’s been busy. But, I’m pleased to announce, (much like a distasteful/annoying/self-congratulatory Facebook post) that this period of my life has paid off, and I find myself currently employed as a full-time, licensed outpatient therapist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel like going through the details of all that the past year has held. Nor do I have the attention span or audacity to write a post of the length that it would require to catch this space up. What I will do however, is start maintaining this space at a more regular clip, and necessarily, it will contain anecdotes and reflections on my journey over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts will also look slightly different, mainly in their form, somewhat in their content. I would like to take a leaf out of a good friend’s book and hone my writing to be more succinct, but I’m afraid that I’m a bit of a windbag on the page. Don’t fear for my clients; I’m less of one in the office (or so I’d like to think…) At any rate however, my posts will be less New Yorker wannabe-esque, and will be more true to this site’s tag line, dispatches. I find myself with snippets of ideas and thoughts throughout each week of therapy that I feel deserve documenting before they drift off into the ether of my mind. With any luck, perhaps someone else finds them worthy also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one update I feel compelled to share relevant to the reboot of this blog, it’s that the most surprising aspect of my experience so far has been my delving, and mainly being &lt;i&gt;pulled&lt;/i&gt; deeper into my faith. I could not have foreseen the importance of faith as such a cornerstone of my work with many of my clients. The vast majority of them are Christians, disengaged Christians, or folks who are interested in pursuing spirituality. I had no idea that I would be so shaped by them and their generous displays of testimony. I also find myself employed by a faith-based organization and surrounded by believers who speak so earnestly about their faith, who are so consistently guided by their faith, that I’ve found it impossible not to admire them and amplify God’s voice in my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll see where this goes, but I can’t imagine this space being wholly secular when my practice is being so guided and informed by my own developments as a Christian. So expect that there will be writings of a spiritual nature on here as well. I’m excited to see what happens next, and to continue to discover my therapy practice; the evolution is my favorite part. There is endless opportunity for improvement, and I’m surprised by my experiences every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest blessing of all is that for all of my efforts, my clients surprise and enrich me tenfold in return. To get to do this every day, for pay, truly seems to me as if I have exploited some tear in the fabric of the universe. To anyone looking for a job where you get to be a pirate for wisdom, plundering more than you sow, become a therapist. You won’t regret it. Stay tuned as I sift through my loot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>To anyone looking for a job where you get to be a pirate for wisdom, plundering more than you sow, become a therapist.</summary></entry><entry><title>From Cocoon to Caseload</title><link href="/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Cocoon to Caseload" /><published>2017-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From_Cocoon_to_Caseload/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a cool 3 months since my last post. How can I be expected to help folks form positive habits when I can’t even stick to my own!? Here’s hoping my clients aren’t looking for some sort of saint-like fellow who has it all figured out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wrapped up my third week of seeing clients and have already learned a veritable ton from my small caseload. I’ve had the pleasure of meeting a teenager with the wisdom and grace of an octogenarian (think Uncle Iroh from Avatar the Last Airbender). I’ve sat with crying folks, afraid that they won’t ever break painful cycles of relationships and harmful habits. Folks who come to counseling scared and worried leave empowered and hopeful for their futures, feeling better just having verbalized it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a magical process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned more over the past three weeks of counseling than I did from all of the collective hours I spent in classrooms and textbooks. The part that I’m most surprised by is that I feel that I take away just as much, (if not more) from the sessions than do the clients. My professors and mentors told me that therapy was a two-way street, but I didn’t fully believe them until I experienced it for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a relief to me too that I’m not expected to just pop out of my grad-school cocoon as some sort of fully-formed master therapist butterfly. The clinic in which I’m doing my ongoing training is wonderful for supporting my growth and for being accepting of my limitations. Likewise, I’m thankful that my supervisors and fellow counselors are pushing me to expand my boundaries and continue to challenge my own assertions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that I believe I need to work on currently is my need for progress. I’m too eager to jump into session with a client and search for immediate answers or solutions to their problems, and I haven’t worked enough on being comfortable with diving into their past in order to search for some of those solutions. They aren’t always sitting on the surface, waiting for us to pick them up and activate them. In time, I aim to become better about holding my breath and going with my clients below the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’ll be no great surprise to learn that my ego must be pruned back further also. My reactions to certain things, particularly clients cancelling or quitting have been far to “me-centric.” It’s hard for me not to assume that the reason for the cancellation or no-show certainly is some reflection of something that I did or didn’t do, when really, it could be any number of reasons that the client didn’t come. Perhaps most simply, it could be that the client wasn’t as ready for the therapy or change process as they initially thought they were. I need to be willing to accept that and support that client in my thoughts and prayers as they await their season of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all else, it’s been a complete blast. I don’t know that I could love the process and art of therapy any more. Even after a challenging session, I find myself smiling with gratitude that I get to do this as a career. I am profoundly thankful for the opportunity and for the lessons my clients have taught me thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try to do a better job writing on here, but I should probably, if we’re being candid, delete the “weekly” from my bio section. I’ll probably have more to write about now that I’m in the throes of counseling, so wish me luck, and look out for more posts soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>&quot;Here’s hoping my clients aren’t looking for some sort of saint-like fellow who has it all figured out.&quot;</summary></entry></feed>
